[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert bluman I have with me Gan
data co-founder and CTO of
cex.io prior to that he was principal
software engineer at Mission Lane Ganesh
is a graduate in computer science of UC
San Diego and he's a creator of the
Python etherpad client Library he
previously appeared on software
engineering radio episode
544 to discuss devops versus Sr in
welcome back to software engineering
radio great to be back today we're going
to be talking about production Readiness
let's start out with
what is production Readiness yeah at its
core it's exactly what it sounds like
it's given a piece of software a
Deployable asset of some sort is it
ready to be in the critical path of
production meaning can it take traffic
can it be monitored can it be managed in
production if there are incidents are
you able to resolve those in a
meaningful way is it secure is it ready
for prime time that is kind of the
essence of production Readiness and it
can be different from organization to
organiz ganization depending what your
requirements are and what you consider
to be production ready but at its core
it's the question of is this ready for
prime time is this service software
ready for prime time I'm sure that all
organizations have always had some
notion of those things but the term
production Readiness as a really
self-conscious coherent entity has some
history how did we get to where it
became a thing I think production
Readiness became as big as it is now in
the the guys with the introduction of
microservices you know if you think
about kind of the macro Trend
microservices were really introduced to
create autonomy for in organizations
right if you have many teams in an
organization how do you give each of
those teams autonomy to move quickly to
deploy on their own and ship extremely
fast and the outcome of that was you
have a lot of teams that are autonomous
and are making decisions on their own
and when it comes to operational
excellence now all of a sudden you have
teams that are doing things in very
different ways and so as an organization
how do you drive consistency around if
something goes down we are able to
operate and resolve this incident very
quickly or we have consistent standards
across organization around what good
looks like for something to be in
production because every team might have
a different definition of that and so
how do we drive consistency around that
so I think that's where we've seen kind
of a Resurgence of this conversation
around production Readiness is we're
kind of moving away this kind of a macro
Trend with microservices as a whole is
we started with just pure autonomy and
now we're thinking about autonomy with
guardrails how do we let teams keep
moving autonomously but put guardrails
in place so that we can operate with
Excellence as a large engine
organization and production Readiness is
one pillar of of that journey I
understood your last point if you had a
monolith then you would have a process
for deciding when to release or not but
with M if you did not have the issue of
how do we ensure that everybody's doing
things the same way you only have that
when you split things into more than one
piece was that your point yeah I think
that's it's mostly true I think it with
monoliths you still kind of had the
issue around it was more like feature
production Readiness like given a thing
I am merging into the monolit like does
this new feature capability I'm adding
meet our production standards around
does it have proper logging auditability
it was kind of more in like the micro
level of like this particular thing I'm
shipping does it do the things I expect
but with microservices it's become more
of this like big picture you know we
need to apply these standards across
every single piece of software in the
organization which I think is just like
a different question of scale it's like
the macro versus micro lens of
production Readiness so when we're
talking about production Readiness is it
a process a set of checklists a meeting
you have what is it that is a great
question I think the thing that we are
trying to
get people to see is it should be a
combination of all the above so maybe
I'll talk you a little bit about current
state and ideal state with production
Readiness today most organizations treat
production Readiness as a checklist or a
meeting or a process it's one of those
three things and generally that looks
like a Confluence page where you know
the your Sr team is going in and
defining a set of standards and says hey
before you go to production you must
abide by these things and if you don't
and like you're not going to go to
production and then maybe you have a
meeting where you go through those
things and somebody comes in and says
look at my service I am production ready
and then you go out to production and
that's kind of where it ends and I think
what we're seeing is like that is the
fallacy of production Readiness is it
needs to be not just a process not just
a checklist but kind of a continuous
process just because something goes to
production and it's Meeting those
standards today doesn't mean it's
Meeting those standards six months from
now things could have materially change
in your production life cycle and so how
do you kind of go back and say like is
this thing still ready for production
like should this thing even be in
production if I were to reassess it
today and you can't do that in a meeting
you can't do that with the checklist and
so how do we kind of rethink what is a
production Readiness process that we
should be going through so that that's
kind of how we're thinking about the the
general problem of production Readiness
I want to Deep dive into all those
things but before we do that I have a
couple other questions production ear is
primarily for shipping a new product or
would this be at the granularity of
smaller like a feature or a PR or a bug
fix what's the granularity of this
production Readiness I would say
generally not PRS in isolation if you
think about your classic kind of feature
that you're delivering or some change
you're making in a PR your automated
unit test your integration test are
probably enough from like a Readiness
perspective I would say in very mature
organizations or Enterprise
organizations with high standards for
excellent you're probably thinking about
production Readiness at least at the
feature level where given a new feature
you're releasing you know the standards
might be different from like a product
level from a feature level at the
feature level you're probably thinking
about does this thing have the right
audit logs does it have the right rback
enforcement within our product does it
have the right Telemetry does it have
product metrics like things like that
you're kind of thinking about more
holistically from Individual feature
level and so like most very much
organizations are doing it at the
feature level most organizations are
still at the kind of service Deployable
artifact level which is can this entire
piece of software being production and
they're not really thinking about
individual features because it requires
like another level of maturity and if
your process is very onerous it takes a
lot of effort even just to do that at
the the service levels you're probably
not going to do it at the feature level
because it's way too way too much
overhead and while we're talking about
the origin what it all means and the
history I have to ask about Google's
impact on this Google has been very
influential through number of books and
best practices in defining the industry
conversation around this and introducing
the term SRE to what extent did this
concept of production Readiness
originate with the Google Sr model it
played a very very big role for sure and
the way it did that is because literally
the introduction of the SR role meant
that organizations were kind of handing
off firstline defense to the SR function
saying if something goes down site
reliability Engineers own the first line
of reliability and they own kind of that
General concept across the organization
and so Sr said like hey we can't be on
call and dealing with fires if we don't
know how to operate your service and so
therefore for us to be able to reliably
operate your service before you hand
your service off to us as first line
defense you must follow these set of
standards and so you'll see it starts to
sound very much like the production
ratings we're talking about in a lot of
organizations they call this you know
the S Readiness Playbook is this service
ready to be handed off to the SRE
organization which is again do you have
the right Telemetry do the right logging
do you the right runbooks like is this
thing something that an SRE who maybe
has no you know context as to the actual
functionality of that service can still
operate that service because it is
mature from an operational perspective
and so now you know we're talking a lot
about you know you build it you own it
or an SRE model or whatever kind of
operational model you have I think that
idea of like this thing is ready to be
operational has now translated into this
broader production Readiness topic and
so yeah the SR guide books and concept
coming from Google definitely had a a
massive impact on the current thinking
around production Readiness I have a
note here which I may have copied
verbatim or maybe this is my own words
in which they Define production
Readiness as the process of onboarding
onto Sr support which sounds to me like
a summary of what you just said would
you want to differ with any aspect of
that I would completely agree I think
the only thing I would add to that is
when you have like Sr Readiness is very
much from the lens of as a person with
no context about this service can I
reasonably operate it which makes a ton
of sense I think current modern
production riness has a few additional
things that have been added to it which
are reflective of the more holistic
version of production Readiness that we
practice today at most organizations
which involves not just like SRE
operational aspects but also things like
security aspects so you know does this
particular service you're trying to
deploy have any outstanding
vulnerabilities you know are you
managing vulnerabilities in a reasonable
format do you have Disaster Recovery do
you have you might even include things
like code quality metrics you know is
this assuming Sr finds an issue and they
can't resolve it and it gets past passed
on to the actual owner of that service
can that owner of the service actually
remediate this issue in production or is
the code too complicated or is there a
high likelihood of there being an issue
because you haven't followed the right
testing practices and so production read
has kind of like grown into the process
of onboarding onto SRE plus kind of the
additional holistic aspects of like is
this thing production ready from a
security platform quality perspective as
well so kind of a super set of of
production Readiness as defined by
Google I would say I don't recall the
date when the SR book was published by
Google may have been around 10 years ago
what you're saying is they really
started the conversation and then it has
evolved in a certain direction since
that time exactly exactly I'm curious
about do you have any stories from your
career of being part of an organization
that adopted production Readiness what
were they trying to get out of it and
how did it go yeah I actually have a
personal anecdote so admission Lane and
and previously lendup I had the
opportunity to drive some of those
production Readiness standards across
the organization and maybe I'll kind of
give you before and after like what even
prompted us to start thinking about
production Readiness and what was the
kind of outcome of driving those
standards so before we kind of started
driving these production reading
standards we had been going through this
monolith to micro macro service you know
Journey for two and a half years or so
and what we found is initially when we
pulled microservices out of the monolith
it was there weren't that many it was
fairly simple to monitor they looked
very much like the microser like the
monolith itself over time we invested in
tooling and infrastructure to make it
really easy for people to spend up
services which was the goal and it
succeeded and people started breaking
things out of the monolith and because
of the size of the organization it was
about 100 Engineers or so were moving so
quickly there were still a lot of
dependencies between services and teams
and things like that and so when you got
alerted in the middle of the night you
it's 2: a.m.
something goes off and you would pull up
a service you like oh my service is you
know running into issues from something
Downstream let me you know go look at
the logs for that service and see if I
can determine something because I have
some context that's not we're not so
massive that I have to escalate and page
that team immediately but then you would
look at that service and you have no
idea where the dashboards are you have
no idea you know the logs are completely
different format from your service and
like the operational overhead of trying
to triage this to when something's wrong
with so massive and that was kind of the
initial prompt for production Readiness
is hey if we standardize the way we do
things from a operational Health
monitoring alerting Telemetry
perspective then when somebody's on call
something goes wrong it'll be way easier
for us to figure these things out
because there's a lot of familiarity
there's consistency and that will make
it easier
when things hit the fan and so we put
together the set of Standards like hey
what do we really care about you know we
care about logging format we care about
request tracing so that we can trace a
request across multiple Services we care
about standard formats for your your
dashboards and they are easily
discoverable they're well documented
somewhere you have a clear escalation
path so if something goes wrong and I
can't figure out what's going on I know
who to escalate this thing to there is a
standard set of metrics that you're
emitting you know things like HTTP
response throughput status codes you
know if you're making additional calls
to external systems are you doing kind
of like pre and post request logging you
know basic things that are like hey if
we all do these things together then
it's gonna make it really easy to to
manage incidents and so we started
enforcing this and we created a
spreadsheet and we said okay these are
all the requirements we're going to go
service by service and we're going to
evaluate them against these requirements
found gaps we resolved those gaps and it
had a massive impact on not just like
our mttr but even the quality of life
for developers because now it's like hey
I'm on call I don't feel like I'm being
thrown to the wolves and it's the wild
west where I'm when I'm when I'm alerted
I know exactly that this information is
available to me and at the very least I
can triage the incident and Route it to
the right person from there on and so we
saw a massive impact in that mttr and
developer quality of life and so that
was kind of like the evidence that we
needed that this production Readiness
process was super impactful it kind of
just created more cohesion in The Way We
Were shipping things even though teams
could you know build in different ways
at the end of it the thing that they
were building kind of looked and felt
the same from an operations perspective
which was which was massive that's great
maybe you could Define mttr and is that
the number one metric you would look at
for evaluating success of a production
Readiness adoption or are there others I
would say there's two aspects so mdtr is
meantime to resolution or meantime
recovery depending how you define it
it's basically how quickly can you get
out of an incident put very simply and
you know the quicker you're able to find
information the more consistent things
are the more visibility there is the
likelier you are to be able to resolve
an incident faster and if you're
following a certain set of Standards you
know this is kind of going back to the
idea of broader more holistic production
Readiness like if you're doing automated
unit testing and all these things you're
probably not going to have those
incidents in the first place and so
generally this concept of like can we
reduce the number of incidents and or if
an incident occurs can we reduce the
amount of time it takes to resolve that
incident are kind of the two big picture
items the third one I will add and we're
seeing this a lot more these days is the
developer experience around incidents
and that's kind of I was alluding to a
little bit there which is the developer
sentiment or happiness or experience
around when an incident occurs do I feel
like I'm in control like incidents are
stressful there's lots of unknown
variables things are kind of all over
the place but within that chaos does the
actual kind of processing information do
you feel like you have what you need to
at least start digging into it or are
you like oh my God this is a black box I
have no idea where to start it's like
there's no information for me so that
sentiment and we're starting to see
sentiment also being captured in like
this this transition from Dora to space
metrics which is you know Dora with
additional sentiment and developer
experience and happiness layered on top
of that I would say for production
Readiness sentiment is also a big part
of that because it's like how to
developers feel when they're on call
given that it's such a high stress
moment for people when they get when
they get alerted great let's delve into
now the big three checklists meeting and
process I'll let you decide where do you
want to start then we'll drill down a
bit into those at a time yeah maybe we
can start with the process and I think
that will naturally segue into the
checklist because there's a lot of lot
of overlap there great production
Readiness is a process how do you
characterize it in most organizations
painful and not always followed and so
to expand on that a little bit further I
would say it's not followed very
frequently because it is painful it is
painful because it's manual and it's
manual because it's usually a manual
checklist and so you can kind of see
where those things start to go a little
hand inand generally the process that we
see in most organizations today is
there's a Confluence page or some sort
of
jira checklist type thing where I need
to attest and validate that I've done a
certain set of things that proves that
my service is production ready I go
through this I fill it out myself and
then I bring this to a committee or I
submit this for approval to whoever the
powers that be are that verify
production Readiness in some cases that
doesn't exist it's just me filling it
out for evidence and me approving it
saying hey yep I'm production ready if
you have an SRE process it's usually SRE
who says Yep this looks good or no you
haven't done these things go back do
these things and it's a kind of
iterative process there and then
throughout this process the the powers
thatb or SRE or whoever are kind of
reviewing this they're looking at your
service and they say cool you are now
green you approved to production and
then I go to prod and that's the end of
the production Readiness process it's
never followed again and never come back
to it that service has been given a
lifetime stamp of approval for our
production Readiness after following
this very manual checklist so that is
the current state in most organizations
of approach Readiness is this a very cut
and dried thing where I'm going through
the checklist and we'll go into what's
on the checklist but let's say one of
the items is logging so I say yes I have
logging no I don't have alerting and so
on or is there a lot more discussion
about what between the people who are
involved in this meeting if do you
really have an adequate amount of
logging based on the product you're
trying to launch have you really done an
adequate amount of planning is it more
of you need to convince Sr that you've
thought of everything to you know
sufficient amount of of depth it's a
great question there's definitely levels
to it I think we definitely see a lot of
organizations where production read this
is literally do you have logging do you
have monitoring you have on car rotation
cool that's all we have the time to
approve right now okay we don't have
capacity from there it kind of goes a
little bit further which is more of a
discussion like are you following our
standard logging format are you doing
request tracing and you have span IDs
and all of your logs that we know we can
trace within a single request as well do
you not only have monitors but do you
have specific types of monitors that we
know are important whether it's very
basic things like CPU and memory and
throughput and things like that but that
you also have you know monitors and
alerts for things that are relevant to
the business functionality of this
service asset lows are a great example
of this where you probably need to have
some standard set of slos like what is
your uptime latency but then do you have
again business level slos that you're
holding the service accountable to and
then from there it gets even more
advanced you know in the largest of
Enterprises we see things like Disaster
Recovery multi-ion backups you know like
have you done load testing and
performance testing do you know the the
spike capacity of this particular
service and how much traffic can it
handle and all those things need to be
evidenced and security needs to do a
review and so there's a wide spectrum of
production Readiness uh depth and
processes that we've seen and some of it
is very much just like a stamp and some
of it's very much like a hey talk us to
your Disaster Recovery what does it look
like how are you going to apply it is
this the right set of metrics are these
too noisy so yeah there's definitely a
spectrum of it that we see across the
board if I was doing a a review of that
type and I was given a question do you
have a multi- region yes no and my
answer is no I don't did we need that I
hope that some of these things which
would have a major architectural impact
would drive the entire product
development life cycle so that by the
time you get to this process hopefully
everything can be checked it is a valid
thought I think this is where we're
seeing more collaboration between Sr and
platform teams these days because
you know when we're talking about
autonomy before autonomy meant that as a
software developer I can just go out and
create my repo and bootstrap some code
and spin up an RDS instance somewhere
and say like all right I got my service
I did I did my job and we're good to go
and then Sr is like whoa whoa whoa oh my
God like what what is this and you know
what we're seeing now is like platform
teams are being reached out to by Sr
teams and saying hey as an Sr team these
are the things that we're enforcing
platform teams can you help us create a
golden path for developers so that if
they want to create an RDS instance
there's like a one-click button or some
sort of workflow they can go through
that's going to give them the database
that they so desire that is already
following all of our SRE principles from
day one so we don't have to go through
this checklist anymore so we're we're
seeing this partnership between the
cloud platform infr teams and Sr teams
who are trying to now give developers a
tool to say if you follow our golden
Pats you're basically good to go we have
codified all of our standards into these
starter kits so that you are good from
day one so we don't having to think
about these things so that's kind of the
next iteration that we're seeing of of
software practices when it comes to
production Readiness as well that's a
great call out I'm going to link to the
show notes we have an episode in our
archives about platform engineering I
don't recall the number at this time but
we'll be in the show notes have you ever
seen a situation where there's pressure
to sweep issues under the rug and agree
that uh production Readiness has passed
just to meet deadlines or product
launches when the service wasn't really
as ready as it should have been I
wouldn't be surprised if it happens
though I think it's more of a visibility
and or manual checking downfall if I
will like I think if there are deadlines
to pass you probably can't go as deep
into the analysis of certain areas as
you might otherwise and so I don't think
because you know the production right is
is directly impacting the developer
experience mentioned like Sr is now on
the hook for the uptime of that service
and developers are going to get paged I
think there's generally an intent to say
hey we we're not going to you know skimp
on these steps but you probably are not
able to go as deep into those those
checklists and say like hey is this are
we just following the letter of the law
or the spirit of the law and I think
that's where things tend to fall apart
more I have a quote from the grafana
labs production Readiness review they've
been very kind to open source their
production ready process to the
community the author who's listed in the
show notes he said we sometimes found it
useful to have the reviewer assume the
role of an attacker who tries to break
the system in review any issues we
identify or filed as product bugs is
that a good practice what's your view on
that that is a great practice and we see
this even in product development a
little bit and this is an interesting
topic because something I've been
thinking a lot about is kind of the the
transformation of some of these roles
like SRE and platform into more product
minded individuals like hey are we
delivering the experience to our
customers whether internal or external
that we care about and so they're trying
to take on this product mindset and the
reason I say that is because in product
organizations you see this concept of a
premortem a lot and we're seeing this in
injuring organizations as well a lot
more frequently but it's the same idea
of like how could this thing fail like
I'm going to spend time pretending like
I'm doing a postmortem and say this is
how it failed and if we can do that
upfront then we well we figured out the
way it would fail and we can assess the
service against that so I think it's a
great practice because it forces you to
think about the failure modes and I
think this is even as a Founder
something we do a lot at the business
level it's like hey what are the ways
that the business could fail and well if
we know the answer to that we can work
backwards and fix those problems before
they actually occur and so production
Readiness is no different like you
should definitely think about it from a
perspective of what could fail here what
are the failure modes for this service
that could cause outages and downtime
then that's your that's your backlog
right there so I I really love that
concept can you give an example of a
premortem or production read review you
involved in that surfaced an error mode
that had not been known yeah so we
actually you know went through this
exercise internally for a feature a
couple years ago which was our
scorecarding product and I won't go into
too much of the details of what
scorecards do right now but you know one
of the things that scorecards rely on
are third- party integration so we
talked to a lot of third party tools and
you probably can kind of see where I'm
going with this at scale you're probably
going to run into a lot of limits from
third party Integrations and so we
talked about that in the premortem and
we said hey this is going to do two
things one it could potentially cause a
whole bunch of noise for us as operators
of that score cing service but B it
could also create outsize customer
impact because I see a bunch of 429s as
a kind of pass through from third party
Integrations that we're pulling data
from and then that's going to result in
a bunch of support tickets and that
functionally is some sort of an incident
and so we said okay well handling rate
limits at scale is quite a hard problem
to do and we've since solved that
problem but we were able to kind of put
the lens of okay how do we solve the
most pressing issues here well one we
need to be able to gracefully handle
these exceptions and 429 errors from
third party Integrations and surface
that to ourselves and meaningful reports
that we're not getting alerted on it but
we still have visibility into it and
then B we need to rethink the product
experience in those cases like what
happens if a third party integration
rate limits Us and how is that brought
to the consumer so it actually was kind
of twofold from the sense of as the
owner of the service that's going to get
paid for this thing how do I make sure
that I have the visibility without
getting alerted for it but then also the
product question that it then brought up
as a result of thinking about the
technical complexity and the technical
failure modes and so we were able to
kind of create a better user experience
as a result of that both internally and
externally the process you outlined it
involved a checklist and a review
meeting now would be a good time to talk
about the checklist I made up a list of
about 20 things that I saw on different
checklists we might not have time to go
through 20 things but what are some of
the more important things that are on
this checklist yeah I think let me talk
about kind of the current state that
we're seeing or like the aspirational
state of production Readiness that we're
seeing from folks I think it starts with
the very Basics which is is there an
accountable owner for the service so
that if something goes wrong we know who
to escalate this thing to is there an
attached on call rotation that alerts
are routed to are we doing automated
unit testing so we're still kind of like
not even thinking about true production
Readiness but it's more of like the
holistic picture so is there automated
unit testing is there a upto date deploy
Pipeline and cicd pipeline these are
kind of like your just simple basic if
you don't do any of this stuff like
let's not even have a conversation about
production Readiness because you're in a
different world altoe then from there we
kind of see like the next level of items
on the checklist which is monitoring
logging Telemetry observability related
so do you have the right set of monitors
a are you emitting metrics to our
ability tool of choice do you have the
right set of monitors and alerts do you
have alerts routing to the right on call
rotation do you have the monitors and
alerts that we believe are useful for
this organization do you have slos
defined for this particular service do
you have runbooks in place so that in
the well-known failure modes you can
easily recover from those do you have a
well documented deploy pipeline do you
have your dashboards in a easily
discoverable place so that people are
not scrambling to try and find the
dashboard when things actually go wrong
and then we get into even more advanced
things in those checklists which are
around security so things like
vulnerability management you know have
you resolved all critical
vulnerabilities and do you have a
process in place to manage those those
vulnerabilities you know things that
sound dumb but are not so dumb like do
the people in your on call rotation
actually have their notifications
enabled so that if something goes wrong
they will actually get paged and it's
not just going to go to den not disturb
and get silenced in the middle of the
night you know do you have dis recovery
processes are you multi- region are
multi- region backups do you have
graceful failover modes you know things
like that are kind of General themes of
things that we see in in production
Readiness checklist you managed to hit a
lot of the items on my list another one
that I have you didn't mention was
capacity planning yeah that one is
interesting because we see that be more
of kind of like a conditional production
checklist item so for example if this is
a tier three service that's not in the
critical path you you know you probably
want to do some sort of capacity
planning but there's some sane defaults
that's going to get you pretty far but
depending on the criticality of this
service which by the way in more mature
organizations is a part of the
production Readiness process is have we
determined the criticality of the
service from a business impact
perspective and then based off of that
determination you know do we need to do
load testing and capacity planning for
this do we have Auto scaling enabled all
those kinds of things become a part of
the process and so you know part of this
checklist can be conditional based off
of the service and the blast radius and
the impact of that service in question
as well we're talking mostly about
ensuring you have enough capacity
another item that I found on some of
these checklists are resource caps and
spend limits to ensure it doesn't go
Rogue and go over budget yes we are
seeing a lot more of that that's a great
call out especially with kubernetes and
things like that it's become a lot
easier to enforce those though we are
seeing in some cases people are trying
to catch that in the actual pipeline or
process itself so you know using Opa
open policy agent or things like that to
enforce that at the city's definition
layer itself versus even having that be
an open question during the production
process which is something probably
worth chatting about is you know the
actual process of filling out this
checklist you know automated or manual
is a whole another discussion in and of
itself so yeah we're definitely seeing
kind of cost caps and things like that
be a part of the process though
generally try and automate those things
as well there are Regulatory Compliance
standards that many organizations adhere
to such as gdpr and S so they sometimes
require you to have certain processes in
place such as incident response
post-mortems are there other processes
that the team has to have you mentioned
that you need to have on call rotation
but what about some of these other
processes yeah I would say mature
organizations or organizations that are
audited or have high compliance
requirements
tend to have kind of a two-phase review
process so production Readiness is
generally going to be the most micr
level version of those compliance things
that you can possibly enforce and so you
can kind of think of as like unit
testing versus integration testing like
production Readiness is almost like the
unit testing aspect which is do you have
non corotation do you have monitoring do
you have alerting and kind of these like
if you don't have these things there's
no way you're going to even meet our
sock to requirements so we're not even
going to bother you know passing you if
you don't have those basic requirements
and then you have a separate kind of
compliance process around okay are you
actually using those things in order to
maintain an inate management process and
things like that so production Readiness
the way we think about is more of like
like I mentioned the unit testing of do
you have the micro components that are
required in order to then operate the
service and then your compliance
requirements are more are you using
those things the right way are you
actually following the process that
those production writing standards then
enable you to do so it's kind of how
we've seen it break out in most
organizations another item I found when
looking at some of these online was
dependencies on other services I could
see that going in a lot of directions
including do we now need to do another
review of those services to ensure they
can handle increased load from having
more clients calling them what are the
implications of that yeah so this is
actually a good question because it
brings up the question of programmatic
or continuous monitoring of production
Readiness because this is a great
example of one of those things that can
change magically and other service
owners have no idea something changed
that impacts the production Readiness
requirements for their services and so
starting with you know if I'm the
service owner a service that is making
calls on something else I have to
consider from a production Readiness
standpoint you know security concerns
authorization things like you know
runbook automation like do I have
visibility into my Downstream services
and the owners of those services so put
differently if I am introducing a
dependency on a service that is not
production ready or is not currently
meeting the production Readiness
requirements it is will be very
difficult for me in real life to
maintain high production Readiness
caliber for my own service kind of like
SLO slos or slas like if you are
dependent on a service with a n you know
95% SLA there's no way that you can
maintain a 99% SLA and so production
riness is kind of similar in that sense
on the flip side if I'm the owner of the
service that's now getting called I may
have no idea that this change has
happened and it may potentially affect
the criticality of my service without me
realizing that and so it actually begs
the question of should production
Readiness be a checklist or should it be
a programmatically monitored and
enforced continuously monitored and
enforced process and checklist so that
these things are automatically detected
and brought to the attention of each
individual service owner as and when
those things happen and so that's kind
of the approach that we have been
coaching people on is you should not
think about production Readiness this as
a checklist where I'm going through a
set of questions because these things
are very hard to catch in checklist you
know because it's so manual and things
could change at any time if I start
depending on a service and they don't
realize that you know I'm not going to
go back and redo my production Readiness
requirement review rather if you can
codify these requirements as
programmatic checks and even the
conditional logic of those checks be
programmatic so you know for example hey
you know you must have a criticality
defined for your service of tier one two
or three by the way you cannot be
considered tier three if you have more
than 10 incoming dependencies in your
service that can be codified pretty
easily and so now if you've codified
those things and you're enforcing them
programmatically well two things happen
one you don't have this question of like
oh what if something like just changes
and people don't realize it but B you
can keep continuously monitoring this
and I can go back to the service owner
and say like hey ganes you your service
that was green on production readiness
is no longer green because something has
changed in its ecosystem so you need to
go back and and resolve this concern
because you're not meeting those
standards anymore and so this idea of
moving away from a checklist to
continuously monitor programmatic
standards is like a paradigm shift in
the way we think about production
Readiness entirely for the reasons you
described you are going in a direction
that answers a question I was going to
ask I'll ask it anyway and then maybe we
can find another angle on it the
question was going to be what type of
tooling do you use to capture the
checklists you mentioned ad Mission Lane
that you had a big spreadsheet I assume
was a shared spreadsheet and everybody
could go and update cells as either yes
or no and just now you're explaining
some of limitations of that approach
what are some of the types of tooling
that either aspirationally might exist
or do exist now for managing the process
yeah it's a great question I think a lot
of folks still use spreadsheets and it
is the vast majority of things that we
see in the wild this is where I do have
to plug cortex a little bit which is
like you mentioned earlier the company
that I'm one of the founders of so we
try to solve this problem through a
product that we call scorecards and so
scorecards are literally a way of
defining a set of standards that can be
verified through integration data and
are evaluated on some sort of cadence
you know a 4H hour 12h hour 24-hour
Cadence and use information about those
services that are defined in some sort
of structured format so I'll give you a
very obvious example you know every
service before it goes into production
needs to have kind of a manifest file
that says this is what the service does
here's who owns it this is the team that
owns it here's the on call rotation for
the service it's links to its dashboards
and so on and so forth so it's like a
manifest file that describes that
service and information about that
service then we take that and we say
Okay given that you can now as a user of
Cortex Define the series of checks you
want to enforce as production Readiness
so you know uh do you have an on call
rotation with multiple escalation levels
do you have monitoring alerting all
these kinds of things we're talking
about can be enforced through code and
then we constantly evaluate your
services against that and we produce
alerts or notifications we say you know
take an age like your service has
dropped its score and production
Readiness from gold to bronze and
therefore you're not meeting our
standards anymore and so folks obviously
can use cortex and scorecards to enforce
those kinds of things or they can build
this programmatically into their cicd
process or you know feed this into a
spreadsheet or whatever that might be at
the end of the day I think the idea is
can you create a system where you're
able to Define this information about a
service in a structured metadata format
so that you can then use that data
continuously to enforce those standards
whether it's through scorecards and
cortex or whether it's through some sort
of cicd automation or something like
that where you're kind of verifying
facts about that service in a
programmatic way so that's what we see
kind of like the aspirations of of
production Readiness are is again just
the automation these kinds of trcks okay
we will link to that product in the show
notes on this topic of dashboards I want
to ask about how you right siiz your
checklist for the size and maturity of
organization I'm sure out of the 20
things we've discussed there could be 20
more or maybe have you been involved in
a conversation within a company about is
it or is it not appropriate to include a
certain item on the checklist
yeah once your production Readiness
process SL checklist becomes religious
in the organization and people have seen
the value and really buy into it then
suddenly it becomes very important that
you're very thoughtful about new
additions to the checklist and the
friction that it's going to add or the
amount of time it's going to take to
enforce these things or you know things
like that are super important and so it
kind of brings me to two things one is
this idea of production Readiness being
binary so I think that's actually
something that we find to be completely
false production Readiness is a
continuous Spectrum you know it's not
just you are very ready or you're not
ready at all you could be kind of ready
you could be very ready or not ready at
all and so it's kind of the spectrum of
how ready are you for production and so
that's the first thing we say is take
that list of 20 30 things you have and
try to bucket that into like Milestones
or levels or whatever you want to call
them some sort of like checklists
checkpoints within the checklist of hey
if you do these five things you're fine
you're okay and then aspirationally and
you know everyone wants to be the best
that they can these additional 10 items
are aspirationally good they mean that
you are meeting a new level of
production Readiness and by the way for
tier one services that is the Baseline
actually so you can't just be you know
at the very basic level of production
Readiness you actually have to meet this
second checkpoint if you're a tier one
service and so can you create this like
aspirational set of checkpoints that
Services can go through over time and so
again it kind of goes back to that
question around you know are people
trying to circumvent your production
Readiness to get to deadlines or
whatever people would do that maybe if
there's like a massive checklist that
I'm never going to complete but if you
think about it from a continuous
Improvement perspective and these
checkpoints it's much easier for me to
say hey just get to that basic level
like it's not that hard these are the
basics and then you can kind of get
better as you go so that's the first
really important thing I think the
second thing is thinking about
visibility into production Readiness so
you know over time you may learn new
things about production Readiness like
you have found a new failure mode across
your organization hey like we've seen
you know multiple incidents happen
because of this particular class of
problem feels like something we should
put in our production Readiness process
well now if you have an automated system
that's enforcing it like scorecards you
can go in there you can codify this new
requirement that realizes really
important and you figure out you know
which services are not meeting that
requirement and go back to them and say
like hey by the way you're not meeting
this requirement you should go and
complete this but this is where
visibility into production Readiness is
really important because as a service
owner if I know when things are coming
when I know what things I'm not meeting
I can have visibility into like oh
there's a new thing that's coming up
this might be on my plate in a month on
my Sprint and so it's like it's not a
shocker for me of like oh my God there's
this mandate coming from SRE and they're
breathing it down my neck and oh my God
I have like 15 tickets I need to
complete for my Sprint already and now
SRE is telling me to do this other thing
it's like no like I see what's coming
down the pipe because it's codified I've
been alerted that this thing is coming
and so it's it's really this idea of
like continuous Improvement Plus
visibility equals a more streamlined
experience of production Readiness so I
don't know if that answers the question
but hopefully that kind helps how we
think about that somewhat could you give
an example of something that would be on
a checklist for tier one service that
might not be on a checklist for a
service that's used by internal
developers during business hours yeah
for like you mentioned earlier capacity
planning or low testing might be a great
example of that so you know if this is a
tier one service you best believe there
is requirements around capacity planning
and lowest testing and do you know the
request throughput that this can handle
and do you know potential spikes that it
can handle you know what is the Baseline
amount of traffic it can handle what are
the spikes that it can handle what is
the target SLA that it's adhering to
does it have an SLO with the proper air
budget so that you know other services
that depend on it can meet their slas so
there's a whole bunch of things around
like you know uptime and quality and
performance that in an internal tier
three service just does not need you
know if something like that goes down
it's probably not the end of the world
you maybe will alert somebody on it and
you maybe they have to meet those basic
requirements of Ru Readiness like if it
goes down there's somebody on the hook
to come and bring it back up but other
than that we're generally fine that's a
great example of something that would
only apply to the most critical Services
versus something internal we've done a
pretty deep dive into these checklists
when we defined what production
Readiness is as a process and invol
checklist and then some kind of review
let's get into the review now is this
review a meeting or
how is it conducted yeah so in most
organizations it's conducted either
asynchronously through some sort of like
Juro ticket process where I'm submitting
my service for production Readiness
review and submitting a packet with all
this information as part of it and
there's some sort of back and forth
there for more complex Services it might
be a meeting where I'm going in and you
know sitting down with the SRE folks and
saying hey let me walk you through this
particular document and how we're
thinking about production Readiness and
that's kind of an assessment that we're
doing together in some cases It's a
combination of both where you know Sr
might come back to you and say like hey
we need a meeting and so it's generally
this kind of like asynchronous manual
process either through ticketing or
through some sort of meeting if you're
using kind of like a scorecarding
solution or an automated system then
it's very much just like it could be an
automated gate in your deployment
pipeline which is like I don't even have
to involve anybody my service has been
evaluated against this and before I hit
the deploy button it's just going to
check are you good are you green yep all
right well you can deploy and there's no
human involved in the process anymore
other than actually codifying those
standards and me following those
standards and so I think that's where
that that process can be different based
on where you are and that maturity of
production Readiness can you think of a
question that you've gotten during our
review and something you didn't expect
and what did you learn from that you
know one of the most surprising
questions I had and this was from like a
really seasoned Sr engineer was about
dashboards you know one of the
requirements on our production Readiness
process was do you have a centralized
dashboard for the service that can be
you know used for monitoring the service
and you're like yeah cool you know slap
a bunch of widgets together you you
think you have your key metrics on there
and you know the first thing we can hit
with it's like okay cool like you this
is fine like it's good enough but have
you thought about is this easy for you
to consume when something's going wrong
like yes you have visibility into it you
can probably drill into it but are you
actually going to be able to use this
dashboard to quickly triage what a
potential root cause is and how would
you think about designing this dashboard
in a way that's easy to consume and it
was such a mind-blowing moment for me
because it's one of those like very
qualitative things about you know
operational excellence but like is this
dashboard actually usable does it have
useful information and you hear this
kind of stuff all the time I know you
know in most cases our day-to-day
operations as software Engineers is not
you know like like flying a plane but
you'd hear this about you know design in
in instruments for planes where it's
like hey displaying information in the
right way is so important because you
need to be able to consume information
very rapidly and the layout and the way
information is displayed is so important
to this and there's no reason why we
shouldn't kind of take that same lens to
our own dashboards that we're building
and so I don't know that was so
fascinating to me that's like yeah I
abolutely should be thinking about my
own dashboard from that lens of you know
information density but consumability
when things are hitting the fan and
sight's down and I'm trying to triage
this thing can I very quickly answer the
questions that I need and get to the
next question the best next step with
the information visualization that's
provided to me so that was absolutely
fascinating that question makes me think
about how the production rating this
process is forcing the service designers
or the service owners to build products
for which the customer is the srre group
if you simply boil it down to a question
of do you have dashboards you say yes we
have dashboards is that really the end
of the discussion or do you need to go
through a product acceptance with your
users who are Sr where they authenticate
into the dashboards they try them and
then they give you feedback about what
they like or don't like or it's pretty
good but could you add this metric isn't
it more of a product development process
than a yes no it's a great point and I
think generally yes
however when we think about how complex
modern engineering organizations are are
I think it's difficult to expect that a
typical application developer has the
same level of understanding around
operational practices as an SRE does I
mean SRE has spent their career
specializing in this thing and so yes
you could have a process that has you
know product acceptance things like that
but you know at the end of the day it's
just going to create so much friction
and I think that's where we're seeing
this kind of going back to that earlier
concept around like platform and SRE and
how they're working together really
mature organizations get to a point
where if I'm using the tools provided to
me by the platform team that is going to
bootstrap me a repository and generate
the boiler play code and instrument the
service with the right agent and
provision the infrastructure I'm also
going to get my dashboards for free my
runbook and pipelines for free like I
shouldn't have to think about this I'm
going to leave that to The Experts I'm
going to follow the golden pths and I'm
going to get out of the box the things
that the experts have determined to be
hey this is what we know is
state-of-the-art that you don't have to
think about it we don't expect you to
learn this we're going to give you the
best experience possible and therefore
my job is easier your job is easier
that's a great developer experience so I
think that's what we've realized is with
all the specialization in software
engineering we're just too far you know
away from expecting application
developers to have that level of
expertise that an SRE or security person
would in we're getting close to end of
time we've hit on all the main points
that I've outlined are there any other
important issues around production
ratings we haven't covered I think the
number one thing that I would want to
cover outside of that is just visibility
and I I know we' brly touched on
visibility but the reason I think it's
so interesting to talk about visibility
is perua is one of those things that
tends to be looked at at kind of the the
front lines of your inur organization
right it's your Sr teams it's your
developers and they're the ones kind of
looking at production Readiness but you
know there's no reason that engineering
leadership should not be looking at the
outcomes of production Readiness right
if we believe in the assumption that
production Readiness is a continuous
process you know it is something that
you can continuously improve over time
then injuring leadership visibility into
hey where are we generally production
Readiness you know are we meeting our
aspirations are we at the very Bare
Bones of production Readiness where are
the teams that are doing the best doing
the worst on production Readiness and so
visibility of production Readiness up
and down the chain is extremely
important
because if for example I see that you
know most teams are just not doing three
of the requirements for some reason and
that's never surfaced to me as a CTO how
am I going to know that there's a gap in
that particular area you know especially
if it's an aspirational requirement but
if I see that I can say hey I'm starting
to see this risk Bubble Up and maybe
it's because we're just not giving our
teams the tooling to solve that problem
and so we can't hold them to that
expectation maybe I need to go and
invest in you know a streamlined low
testing capacity test in platform so
that we can meet those requirements
because we're making it way too hard for
developers and so driving that
visibility up to chain and even
including production Readiness threshold
and standards in like all hands hey 80%
of our teams are meeting you know the
highest level of press Readiness by the
way that drove down our mttr on these
teams by 30% look at the big wins you
know we should you know aspire to get
the remaining 20% up that is going to
drive this culture of excellence and it
makes your Sr team's job a lot easier
because sres are tasked with a
Monumental job of trying to get people
to care about these things and enforce
these standards but if your leadership
is looking at this stuff too and driving
that visibility it completely changes
the conversation and now it's a thing
that the entire organization is kind of
rallying behind and I'm able to now use
that to assess risk in a way that I
wasn't able to before so that's the last
thing I wanted to mention is like hey
make this something your leaders care
about to not just your sres not just
your developers it's for everyone Y is
there anywhere on the internet you'd
like to point people yeah you can
connect with me on LinkedIn or follow me
on Twitter I talk a lot about the stuff
is something near and dear to my heart
as a developer like everyone else I hate
getting paged in the middle of the night
it was my worst nightmare and so if Ru
Readiness and things like this are one
way of reducing that pain then it's
something that I really care about so
yeah definitely follow me on Twitter or
LinkedIn and I love to post about this
kind of stuff Gan I'm gonna wrap up here
thank you very much for speaking to
software engineering radio about
production Readiness thank you so much
for having me this has been Robert
bluman for software engineering
radio thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
i e software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all episodes of SC radio
is licensed under creative comments
license
2.5 thanks for listening